hello everyone and welcome to this
impromptu panel of experts on the 24
hours of dma compliance with apple I
have not slept much so please excuse any
David regulatory capture doesn't help
you sleep at night like it does me uh
no so those of you listening on the sub
Club podcast this is a live recording
Friday less than 24 hours from the
announcement of Apple's compliance with
the dma so let's do a quick round of
intros let's kick it off with Gabriel I
actually don't know Gabriel so happy to
learn a bit about Gabriel and Runway ml
real quick for sure so Gabriel one of
the founders of Runway we are a mobile
release management platform we work with
medium to larger Siz mobile team so I
think a bit of a interesting perspective
here and excited to chat with you all
thanks for having me awesome Nico I'm
Nico I'm the founder of adjacent which
is an early stage fund focused on the
mobile ecosystem so I invest in a lot of
consumer subscription companies prum
subscription company and incredible
infrastructure companies that support
them Jacob I'm the chief poster here at
Revenue cat I've bigest beard I think by
a mile and I achieved it all without
regulation which is really what's
important I'm excited to use the
research of other people to add hot
takes to what happened I think everybody
knows what Revenue cat does at this
point but give us 10 seconds we we help
developers make more money and so Yen
who a second David and everybody
internally have been scrambling the last
24 hours or whatever to figure out how
and if developers can make more money
with these changes but we make
infrastructure for processing payments
on App Stores and Beyond so it's been an
interesting 24 hours for us and yens
yeah I'm head of product at Revenue cat
and Jacob stole all my thunder that's
what we've been thinking about what does
this mean for Revenue cat the product
but then also again all of our customers
because in the end that's what we're
here for helping developers make more
money Yen did spreadsheets Nico did
equations so
between David and I we just have to do
hot takes it's gonna be a fully informed
session all right and then I'm David
Bernard growth Advocate at Revenue cat
so I host a subcl club podcast run the
community and do a bunch of just random
stuff like staying up all night reading
European
regulations to help our developers make
more money and what's going all right so
I wanted to kick it off with what is the
dma so I'm going to just read a couple
of highlights and we'll go around the
horn to kind of fill in any details I
missed but essentially the digital
markets act the dma designate certain
large tech services as quote Gatekeepers
which must comply with the new
obligations and rules by March 2024 so
that's why we're hearing the news
yesterday is because the compliance was
mandated as of March but the G
Gatekeepers were only announced 6 months
ago although most of The Gatekeepers
probably knew that they were going to be
announced as Gatekeepers and then just
to give folks a taste I'm going to read
one of the provisions a short one from
the dma so this is on the provision for
alternate inapp purchases and outof app
payments the gatekeeper shall not
require end users to use or business
users to use to offer or to interpolate
with an identification service a web
browser engine or payment service or
Technical Services that support the
provision of payment services such as
payment systems for R out purchases of
that gatekeeper in the context of
services provided by the business users
using that catee Keepers core platform
Services I've already quit making
apps hot takes let's go around the room
like what is a dma give it to us in
simpler terms Jacob you start because I
know yours can be the spiciest take well
okay so I for when was this passed this
was like 2022 that it was I still don't
understand how the laws work in Europe I
ask every time I'm with a European
person and that doesn't usually help but
this is an EU law meaning it was passed
in Brussels at the European Union level
to regulate I guess it's because that
the EU regulates Commerce don't ask me
about the politics of it I don't really
understand that but essentially this was
a regulatory move to essentially limit
the power of a handful of mostly
American companies and folks on the list
are like meta Google Apple bite dance I
Believe made the list there's a couple
others and it has a bunch of stuff
across different vertical but then
specifically there were Provisions in
here that Were Meant to hit at Apple's
earned Monopoly on the App Stores which
there's been agitation from folks like
Tim Sweeney at Epic and others that the
30% spy especially Spotify yeah I guess
in ter constituents they're probably the
biggest one that's complained that this
is just highway robbery it's unfair we
need the government to come in and make
you know Apple's not being forced by the
markets to compete at a fair number here
and so my understanding is the dma was
meant to force Apple to respond to
Market well I don't know respond to what
I guess respond to what European
Regulators wanted so that's my take Yen
can you give a like slightly more
balanced take on it I don't know as a as
a European
you're you're the closest geographically
to Brussels I
believe my Representatives had a say in
this yeah why did you vote for this yens
please explain to no so I think the
positive T of this is obviously like
instilling competition fostering
competition in the payment space where
you can basically say well if you want
an iPhone you have to go through apple
and then the question is kind of like
back in the day with Windows and the
Internet Explorer is there some kind of
unfair tying going on of the store and
the device and the platform right so I
think that's kind of the intention right
the intention is just more competition
provide alternative options so that
there's some real Choice going on where
right now if you want to be on iOS you
have to be on the app store if you want
to be on the App Store you have to use
in a payment so that is I think like the
positive spin a create a Market within
iOS right within ex exactly because
obviously there is a market between IOS
and Android right and also if you look
at iOS versus Android Android has always
had a bit of a different rule set even
though Google over time has tried to I
guess make Google play more of the only
Avenue and kind of gotten closer to
Apple's regulations but certainly iOS is
still the more lockdown environment
right so I think that's kind of the
positive spin on the regulation itself
at least the intent of the regulation
let's put it like that Nico Gabriel
anything to add to that summary of the
intent and other provisions of the dma I
would personally leave the payment stuff
to The Experts from our perspective
we're moving from a place where Apple
has monopolized the paperwork and the
extra sort of information you need to
supply when you're submitting releasing
your apps and that continues there's
just more of it so it's seeming like the
installation sheets the labeling that
has to happen it's still very much
controlled by Apple there's more
hopefully on the other side of all that
extra work that you get out of it but it
still comes with headaches and it's
still very much controlled by Apple so
we view it from that perspective more
work more hassle more paperwork and not
fun stuff that comes with getting your
apps out the door so I guess my
overarching comment would be that I do
believe that the EU likes to regulate
and you can judge that one way or
another but I think in this case
specifically it does come with more
options so you can default to the status
quo which means it does not harm if you
just consider where we are today but
then it opens up an alternative and I'm
sure we're going to talk about that a
lot and how good or bad it is and when
it actually makes sense to opt for that
but I do believe that in this case
actually there will be Innovation coming
from it which is weird right because
usually EU regulation is maybe counter
that and I think that in this case we
will actually see some new things that
are not possible today and I think that
is a positive we all probably agree the
intent behind the dma is good I think a
lot of our hot takes on the dma being
bad is more just the bureaucracy of it
all I mean personally and even
professionally I wish for more
competition and more openness and
everything else and I think that's was
the intent of the dma but part of the
reason I read that excerpt is that
anytime you do regulate it's such dense
wording you're trying to cover cases you
can't predict and otherwise but I do
think this opens a door and I think to
Nico's point and one thing to recognize
too is like this is the start of
negotiations this is not the end of
negotiations so as we talk through the
details here like the EU is going to
have a chance to say no apple actually
we're gonna find you two billion dollar
if you don't change it in this way based
on third party conf now that's going to
be litigated over months and years but
this is a starting Point not the end
point kind of skipped over summarizing
what actually impacts the em like
Gabriel was kind of alluding to there's
kind of multiple parts of this like one
is there's a whole new mechanism for
deploying apps essentially Sid loading
but it's very regulated it's very
controlled it's not like Enterprise
distribution where you could just
download an app that's signed with some
kind of CT there has to be this there's
this intermediary Marketplace thing that
they created which requires all these we
could do a whole podcast just on like
what it takes to create the marketplace
then there's I think the second big
pillar that's probably of concern for
this audience is the new business terms
I think that's also Up For Debate and
then I guess like thirdly there's which
would probably be my most exciting thing
to talk about would be the meta game of
what's going to happen in the meta
strategy of the EU versus Apple versus
epic Etc so we've got an overview the
dma big European regulation well
intentioned is going to absolutely
change some things this is a starting
point so now let's talk about Apple's
response to the dma because that is
exactly how it's going to play out is
how app
responded to the dma and then I think we
can also intertwine some opportunities
where the EU may actually Force some
changes that will create even more
opportunity so yeah let's start with at
a high level those three things like
what are the big changes with
Marketplace what are the big changes
with fees and what are the other big
changes that it enables let's start with
the most simple one then is the fees and
Jacob you started that so you can chose
your own adventure yeah CH your own
adventure in the European Union by Tim
Apple can't wait you can choose these
new capabilities or you can default to
the status quo there's two new business
models there's the old business model
and then there's the new business model
if you want to be distributed in one of
these third party stores you have to use
the new business model I think correct
me if I'm wrong stating however you
cannot use a third party store and still
use the new business model decision tree
step one yeah so every developer gets to
make this Choice do I choose the new
business model or do I stay on the old
business model Apple has not indicated
that this is a two-way door David's got
some rumors he's heard that maybe it's a
two-way door but like we have not heard
anything and so that's I think the first
thing is what is this new deal and is it
good for developers or not we've talked
about this before also I think at
different points that there's already
been a trend of mobile first companies
starting to move some of their
conversions online to circum vent the
Apple cut and that is a natural motion
there's been sweetheart deals with some
of the bigger companies so I think that
this has been a long time coming and to
me it opens up a lot of doors you can
stick with what is there but you also
can opt into your own payment methods
which means a lot of payment companies
will come after this Revenue cat will
have some kind of role in it and I think
it is going to be interesting to
understand what other options it opens
up that were not suited for the existing
Apple Store payments and specifically
because I've been working with a few
companies that are prosumer and have
somewhere consumer applications
distribute to the Appo but then also
have Team functionality or B2B and parts
of their product and for those it's
always been really hard to move from a
solo product to an actual multiplayer
product and I think specifically for
that this could be a GameChanger because
if you can start adding seats and use
your company's credit card on mobile to
create Company accounts it is very
different than having to do it with your
Apple ID where you have your personal
credit card and things like that so I
think it just opens up different
Alternatives it won't make sense for
everybody and I think the tricky PO is
actually figuring out for who it makes
sense but I do believe more options in
this specific area are a good thing that
will lead to innovation in terms of the
types of products that we can charge for
and how we can charge for them I'm
excited about it yeah so maybe it would
be worth summarizing the new fee
structure first at first glance it kind
of looks attractive because the numbers
that you see first when you read through
Apple's documentation are 10% and 177%
that basically replace the 15 and 30%
typical Apple cut however then when you
read the fine print it actually starts
to get a little bit more murky so
firstly for the payment itself Apple now
charges 3% so that means you end up at
13 and 20% so if you're using iip yeah
exactly if you're using an purchase
which in that scenario that Nico was
describing wouldn't be the case right
yeah yeah right right let's take one
step back cuz I think forming it as this
decision tree is actually really helpful
because then it separates all the
different kind of models that you can
blend and then we can go through the
details of each of those models so the
first decision tree as Jacob said was
you can stay with the old or you can
switch to the new but when you switch to
the new there's actually four separate
models and so let's start with the
overview of those four models and then
we'll dig into the details of each of
those four models so the first model is
that you stay distributed through the
App Store and you keep billing with
apple and that's what yens was alluding
to so that one we'll get into the
details but that's an option the second
option is you can be on the App Store
and use alternative payments the third
option is that you can be in a
marketplace with third-party payments
and the Marketplace app we need to dig
into that but Marketplace app has all
these different regulations and
everything else the fourth option is
that you can actually be both in the App
Store and be on a Marketplace app and so
it gets really complex and this is the
part that I think is going to be maybe
most helpful for the listeners today is
breaking down these four different
options and the benefits and drawbacks
of each because this is the decision
developers are specifically going to
have to make it's like okay if I accept
the new terms there's four two your own
Adventures what are the things that
happen in each of these four so that I
can make an informed decision on whether
this could potentially be good for my
business those aren't like formal
choices though like they are with
choosing the business model that's like
thing to select and then the other four
these are like four things you can can
float between different techniques yeah
so then let's start with that first one
and yens that's where you were kind of
at is that the very first option is that
you accept these new terms you stick
with the App Store you stick with app
store billing so then what's the deal
that you get by accepting these new
terms but staying in the App Store and
staying with app store billing if you do
the math you see that it's going to be
basically the 30 and 15% that Apple
standard rates dropped to 20 and 133% so
that means 20% instead of 30% for Big
Ups and subscriptions in their first
year and 133% instead of 15% for
developers in the small business program
and subscriptions from their second year
however and that's kind of where a lot
of the questions I guess come in in all
of these options this core technology
fee comes in and this core technology
fee is 50 cents per first annual install
per year once you've fit a million
installs threshold and the interesting
thing there that's very easy to miss if
you're just reading how this metric is
called is that this includes not only I
tap the button in the App Store to
install it also includes app updates so
basically for any app that continuously
ships app updates you can kind of think
about this as the number of people in
the EU that have the app on your iOS
phone right I mean that's basically what
will count against this metric there
right so obviously like if you're a
small developer who is nowhere close to
hitting a million in downloads basically
you can ignore that but as soon as you
cross that threshold it can become very
expensive very quickly because again
that's a 50 cents for every install then
after that threshold you put some scale
numbers on this yens and a doc like how
many EU iPhone users are there I mean
certainly between 100 and 200 million
probably something of that order so if
you're an app that's beyond 1 or 2%
penetration into the market you're going
to be in the range exactly it's
certainly not your like average India
app but there's definitely enough apps
and I think this core technology fee you
know you can clearly read this as trying
to dissuade bigger companies to go on
this new model right because for bigger
companies it's going to get really
expensive really quickly and that is I
think a little bit of the poison pill in
this whole Arrangement because that's
just going to mean whatever it is like
going on a third party app store is
probably just not going to be attractive
for a big app because it's going to be
really really expensive to accept those
new terms and then any third party app
Marketplace won't have big apps so
therefore does that Doom them already
but okay you know maybe I'm kind of
going too far into interpretation and we
should like Zoom back out and look at
the other the other three models that
David yeah but before we move on to that
one and we talked about this a lot
internally yesterday and so Jacob I want
your take on this is that even if you're
an indie accepting these new terms in
the hopes of saving some money on
fees yeah you save 2% you do open
yourself up to risk and I think that
that's the biggest thing for folks
thinking about this is that offside
chance but if your app goes viral for
some reason if Apple features it if you
get a lot of press or whatever by
signing up to these new terms you risk
that if you do grow your business if
something happens you introduce a hot
new feature whatever happens you're
taking a lot of Risk by we had a very
interesting discussion yesterday about
something I think it's discussed in
society is like how do you quantify and
deal with tail risk right like how do
you as a developer enter into a debate
of well I can have 2% discount which
relative to Apple's 2% of 15 is not
insubstantial it's like maybe 12% or
something of the whole amount of fees
reduction but like with now you're
accepting this this potentially
catastrophic risk that if your app goes
viral which your app's not going to go
viral I can tell you that I love you I
want you to be successful but I can say
to everybody your app's not going to go
viral and be right 999 times out of a
thousand right but everybody's a
temporarily embarrassed fir rot
Millionaire right so it's not very easy
to like think about this risk we see a
lot of apps here there are apps that
we've done case studies with you look
for them that have gone viral that
monetization wasn't their biggest thing
so they have a relatively low LTV tons
of downloads this was the beauty of the
old models Apple bore all the costs they
took care of everything this developer
just shared their revenue at 15% maybe
30 and it was all upside for them under
this new model that could literally syn
like I ran some analysis on situations
like this with some customers in ours
their customers millions of dollars in
the hole on CTF on the core technology
fee I have to imagine Apple's not going
to come take your company right like I
imagine they're probably gonna have a
like okay this was beyond your control
whatever but like as a developer it's
going to happen like somebody's going to
accept these terms somebody's going to
end up becoming a viral hit and then
they're going to owe Apple millions of
dollars and I'm sure Apple will let them
out the back door I hope maybe but it
does create this really you know and
this is the whole reason we liked the
Rev share model just developers just had
basically no risk and now you're
introducing risk honestly I don't know
how to think about it's really hard to
underwrite tail risk events like that n
what's your perspective on this specific
I know you're kind of bullish on
Alternate payments and side loading and
things like that but as a venture
capitalist who wants to your portfolio
companies succeed at a high level do you
see any of those portfolio companies
taking this deal and we'll talk about
the other deals later but what do you
think about this deal specifically I
think what I tried to do yesterday with
the formulas is figure out because like
the way I think about is if you're upset
about it stick with the status quo for
most companies this is the right choice
especially if it's big volume low
average revenue per user it doesn't make
sense the companies it doesn't make
sense for are those that convert the
users to to a high degree and then have
a high yearly plan and don't have that
many free users that retain after the
first year that is basically what comes
out of it and we don't have to be
specific about it but basically if you
have a yearly plan and a conversion rate
and you multiply both and it's bigger
than five then it makes sense this is
what the numbers say and then for the
second year renewals it's basically 25
EUR per user that remains and it's
includes the free and the paid users
that you have to have in the annual sub
same or more to benefit from it and what
that means is like there's a small
percentage of companies that have really
high conversion that have almost no free
users or a hard pay wall with none and
for those companies they can save five
plus percent of their margins which is a
lot right like it can be a big benefit
plus there's one last thing that I want
to say to this is you have a
considerable unknown which is if we do
have new app stores emerging which is
going to take time it's a chicken and
egg problem nobody's going to want to do
it initially because there's no
distribution slow slowly some of the
Pioneers will do it and it will create
something that will offer the developers
the ability to distribute with lower
fees which is another added benefit that
is really hard to foresee at the moment
this small Universe of like high
conversion High subscription companies
which is the majority of the companies
I'm working with they can benefit from
it but you have to really look at the
numbers as long as that's a really
significant free component to the app it
gets more difficult but I do believe
that this will also lead us to think
about this in a new way how much value
do you really get from the free that
stay with you for longer than a year if
they don't convert right and we can look
into this we can dig into this we can
look at the numbers and it might need
some violence to like how we use the pay
wall and adjust features but I think
there is going to be companies that will
benefit from it it's going to be a small
cohort something you said there Nico
which we were talking about this morning
on Twitter and this is the unknown is
you can put up a hard pay wall you can
discourage users from using on free you
can eliminate your free plan but you
can't make them delete the app you can't
this app will self-destruct if you do
not convert in 10 days and so that's the
big unknown on how many people actually
are going to delete their apps it's not
zero it's probably a majority the Decay
rate of people deleting apps I don't
know somebody maybe Gabriel knows like I
don't know I agree maybe it doesn't
compound to much but I think that's the
thing I'm having a hard time quantifying
yeah agreed yeah and I actually just
launched a hard pay wall in my app
yesterday and can tell you it would not
be a very good opportunity for me I mean
even on the highend you're talking like
a 25% I think is what I'm landing at for
my app over the last 24 hours of a trial
start rate so that means 75 out of every
hundred people I'm paying 50 cents for
them to install and they don't even
start a free trial so like the math on
this does start to get difficult when
you're a free app to download Nico how
are you thinking about the risk of even
these very high performing High
monetization apps who are a free
download where you're doing a lot of
user acquisition through paid ads and
you have very tight control of
purchasing very high intent users and
then converting those users well there's
still that risk because you're a free
app that you could just have a ton of
downloads from low intent users so
that's like a risk even for like highly
monetized apps Revenue c new product
should be insurance no against yeah the
thing honestly they this is something
somebody should sell a policy against
right I'm not sure who's going to have
the data to underr it but I dare to
think that even there must be some
protection mechanism from Apple for this
not maybe for the case of like a
well-funded well monetizing company that
has the resources but they do not want a
small developer going viral and then
being bankrupt that is enti their right
like that's not what they want to get
out of it so there's going to be some
protection I'm positive maybe it's going
to be difficult to understand it at
first but I would be very surprised if
that is not the case there is cases
where it's not clear I will not say that
after 24 hours I have a perfect view on
it I just have the view of like for
these companies it does make sense and
for some companies that's a big question
mark because we have to understand the
data better right so like understanding
how many free users are still around
after a year understanding the
conversion rates better making sure that
we have the right pricing and such I
don't have the perfect answer for it yet
we just need to dig into it to see if it
does make sense and it might not make
sense initially and that's okay and the
question is like does it make sense at a
later point in time and under what
circumstances does it make sense and
could it make the business better and
that's the question that as a result
from the iOS changes paid acquisition
there was like a year or two where
people struggled a lot but a lot of the
companies that I work with came out much
stronger there's a higher organic growth
component they found more creative ways
to do marketing we're not pouring money
into mattera although that is still part
of the strategy for many of them but
it's just not as important of a
component and I think that here there
will be a similar education we will just
have to learn what are the criteria that
gives us an advantage if we adopt a new
model and really understanding those
levers and I think there's going to be a
big big gray area and there's G to be an
even bigger like it does not make sense
area and in the gray area I think it
probably the default is you don't do it
the case you mentioned Nico that to me
seems like I would take a risk on as an
entrepreneur is the multi-seat mode
discussion so like if you I use notion
as an example or something like this
where you're a multiplayer SAS app and
your whole thing is predicated on seats
and there's really no reason to go viral
there's really no consumer motion to it
I think that might actually out where
you're paying maybe your customer LTV is
$30 a month or something like this you
can really easily bear that 50 cents a
year you can even argue that for some of
those companies the mobile first
consumer motion is actually a top of
funnel for the Enterprise motion and
from that perspective it can make sense
right it's part of the acquisition
couple people that trickle in are 50
cents so so that's an unknown it's also
a new model like we'll have to see more
but I believe in that and then the
second part I mentioned just quickly
right now we assume there's going to be
no other marketplaces because it's going
to be super hard to get it kickstarted
but somebody's going to build it and
some people are going to fortnite is a
good example right epic is going to do
it they're going to start experimenting
and from that there will be more
audience and once there is alternative
marketplaces with big audience the math
changes again because yes you still have
the same C on the App Store but you have
lower costs on the new app store and so
it Nets again more positively for the
business it's just a more longterm
consideration let's wrap up this section
with Gabe and then we'll do step number
two on the Choose Your Own Adventure and
then step number three will be
marketplaces where we can dive deep on
what that could mean so Gabe any
thoughts on sticking with the App Store
but just getting lower fees yeah I mean
you said wrap up hopefully it doesn't
open cans of worms my question for
everyone is are there any parallels to
draw from the Android side and I hate
bringing that up I know we have an iOS
leaning crew here no we're equal
opportunity App Store people we love
both but you know like things have been
a little more in this direction on the
Android side for a while is there
something to learn in there do you all
have opinions from that side of the
house my opinion would be that if you
were to just draw out like what is the
ability to have alternative stores on
Android mean for iOS the answer is very
little right like I think that's the
answer as optimistic as I am and I think
my take for the last like 24 hours has
been like apple didn't get this Monopoly
by Kolling the government they didn't
get this by like having a monopoly on
some finite resource like railroads or
cables Under the Sea they got this by
building the best phone and everybody
buying it and nobody wanting to buy
anything else right and so it's going to
be very very hard to force people to do
something when I think consumers have in
a lot of ways voted it's not a perfectly
free market but I think people have this
like sense that Apple's unkillable that
the only way that the iPhone's ever
going to be toppled that the app store's
ever going to be toppled is if the
government or like we forc them to
through regulation or whatever but it's
historically not been the case like
technology has not lasted that long
Nokia and rim ruled the world and
eventually people are like this sucks
Apple was like how about we do it less
sucky and 10 years later those two
companies are gone I don't think there's
any reason that won't happen and maybe
this just opens that up so what Nico is
saying is like maybe epic store does
rock and everybody wants to use it okay
then maybe I'll take my words back and
the dma was really important for like
opening up that light maybe it's undo
burden to expect a competitor to build
the phone then build the App Store maybe
that's the world it should be but again
like why didn't epic just build an
Android device you could just buy one
and make it the fortnite phone and all
that stuff and the answer is because
most of the money is on the iPhone and
the iPhone users and it's the best
device right like that's why this is
getting into the meta metas I don't want
to get too ranty on and then maybe to
add on even there's a certain aspect of
people buying iPhones because the
experience is more controlled right and
there's maybe few degrees of freedom but
also less crap so you know there are
options right like you can go by an
Android phone and do all kinds of crazy
stuff you can get your emulators on
there you can like do your piracy or
whatever else stuff you want to do you
can get the like epic side loader it
exists but it's not successful because
the experience isn't there and you can
blame Apple you can't blame Apple for
that I don't even think you can blame
Google for that because the scare
modeling for Sid loading on Android's
pretty minimal it's pretty like oh yeah
be careful right but that's it and it
still hasn't taken off so I think well
the reason for that is there was a
question in the chat asking why hasn't
any of the alternative app stores on
Android taken off and I think it's just
a question of incentives for some of the
players that are able to pull this off
right because for most of the companies
I work with even if they're
crossplatform they have maybe 20% of the
revenue coming from Android and
oftentimes it's even from GEOS that have
a lower subscription pricing in Revenue
per users I think it's a very different
incentive at this point to figure out an
App Store that works on Apple than it
was to do it on Android and I think
there's going to be a lot more resour
just put behind it yep it's 20% of so
it's five times more Revenue it's not
like 500 times more Revenue so like I
have to think there's enough there
should be enough there to get something
started and it hasn't seemed like that's
the case but I don't I don't know I
can't well let's skip over choose your
Adventure 2 because this one is we have
a blog post that explains
everything yeah check the blog post
because it'll explain all this in depth
but Choose Your Own Adventure number two
would be to stick with the App Store but
use alternative payments you can either
do app alternative payments or you can
link out to the web the payment terms
are very similar to sticking with the
App Store you still pay a commission and
then you still have the core technology
fee and everything else so that's kind
of a spin on what we've already been
talking about yeah let's Jump Ahead to
these marketplaces because I do think
this is a really important part of this
regulation and like yall were saying it
is the
long-term maybe biggest crack that's
going to form because of the dma but the
first thing to understand about
marketplaces there's going to be so many
caveats along the way but the first
thing to understand about these
marketplaces is one apple has to approve
any Marketplace and the marketplaces are
the only place that you can sideload so
this is not opening up sideloading where
any random app can be hosting that
random app on their random website and
you can just download it the side
loading has to come through approved
thirdparty Marketplace apps those
Marketplace apps have to put up a
million dooll line of credit with that
apple is saying is a way to ensure that
consumers are protected that it's not
some Fly by Night company launching this
Marketplace app but somebody with some
amount of resources to support the
developers and support this Marketplace
app so that if consumers get scammed if
there's problems there's some level of
recourse versus like a Fly by Night
Marketplace app that just scams a bunch
of people there's been a lot of
condemnation of that but that part of it
I do think is actually very much like
apple protecting consumers in the EU no
you can debate do they need that
protection should it just be total open
side loading like the Mac whatever but
that's how Apple has defined this next
opportunity in the choosey Adventure is
that a big company like fortnite can
create this Marketplace you as a
developer can then choose to participate
in that Marketplace a couple of more
caveats before we open up to discussion
in the fine print we found all sorts of
other gotas one is that the marketplace
itself has to play the core technology
fee so if all Epic did was create a
Marketplace app and only sell fortnite
every download of the marketplace incurs
a core technology fee and every update
of the Marketplace app incurs a
technology fee and then every install
and subsequent annual update of fortnite
incurs a core technology Fe this is
going to be very expensive a fake store
right with one app in it that's the
intent of that I think this is maybe the
again the more interesting thing to talk
about here because there could be
marketplaces that limit installs to not
incur the technology fee maybe there's
some prerequisits to even get into this
Marketplace app and so this is maybe the
less risky way to take advantage of the
dma is to set up a Marketplace that
protects against this core technology
fee syncing your business so let's talk
about this the last thing on the core
technology fee and then actually again
if you want to jump in with any details
I missed before we do our pantry all
around but core technology fee is the
only fee that you pay so inside those
marketplaces you can use any payment
provider you want you don't pay Apple
any commission you don't pay Apple any
billing fee the only thing you pay Apple
in these marketplaces is the core
technology fee did I miss anything and
if you use iip right like you can still
use use I no you cannot use from my
understanding no no
no and they're not charging commission
so they're not taking no they're only
taking the core technology fee in that
case did you say that we cannot do in
purchases in the no you you cannot do
not using app but in the third party
Marketplace store you can use Apple pay
to pay with your face processed via
stripe in Revenue cat yeah that's yeah
exactly I mean that's it doesn't matter
really right yeah yeah and this is this
is by way interesting that this is
explicitly allowed to use Apple pay I
was kind of surprised when I saw this in
the docs that they explicitly talk about
using Apple pay and how you have to use
Apple pay but it didn't seem like
prohibitive you know yeah like they
would make a weird rule like oh can't
use Apple pay right it would seem like a
dumb thing they would add yeah I guess
one one kind of minutia is that there is
going to be at least two scare sheets in
these steps so you see the scare sheet
for downloading this Marketplace app and
then through the no diarization process
from what I understand apple is going to
kind of document some things and there
will be a second scare sheet when you're
installing an app from this thirdparty
Marketplace that is kind of an apple
system sheet that tells you about what's
happening in the app but all in all it's
kind of like what you were saying Jacob
is like is that fairly reasonable to
prompt I mean Apple the wording of it
the design of it maybe over the top but
it's two hurdles to get to a completely
free and open ecosystem on iOS one scare
sheet to download The Marketplace app
one scare sheet to download the app
itself and then you can do pretty much
anything that's allowed via these
notorized apps so what do we think
there's a lot of angles here and again I
would leave the payment stuff to The
Experts I think going back slightly one
of the most interesting things for us is
all those rules around setting up the
new marketplaces and one of the results
of that being that a lot of these big
names that might be interested in
distributing more directly to their
users really can't you need to set up a
Marketplace that is designed as an
outlet not just for your own app but
others and there would be potentially
this big shift in larger teams and
companies to distribute directly to
their users if they already have sites
that have a lot of traffic that kind of
thing just make it super easy to get
more folks onto mobile not possible so
to make this all happen in a big way we
talked about someone in the comments
like a Netflix or Spotify there are some
big names there that could do a sort of
Niche or vertical specific maybe
Marketplace but when you look broader
scope for large companies it's hard to
see how
they would expand Beyond more
traditional ways of Distributing I think
that's how we view it right now there's
just so many guard rails on this that I
think eventually things will expand and
get there but it will be extra slow I
think because of some of the red tape of
course yeah Netflix is an interesting
one because Netflix has a real cogs
problem right like they can't charge
$9.99 or whatever on iip because they
have to pay a bunch of fees for their
licensing of content they can always
just Jack the price up but they don't
like to do that either so they've just
said forget it we drive enough traffic
you could see a world where they're like
okay let's build the Netflix app store
which like TBD I wonder how strict
Apple's going to be and be like all
right the Netflix app store is just for
Netflix we're not going to allow this
right like this is not really an app
store right this is just a special thing
for Netflix but Netflix also is doing
app distribution they have games now and
stuff like this so they're kind of
already playing in this space so you
could see them building this the
question for Netflix would be is all of
those steps going to compound to 30%
that you're losing already and I'm like
30% comes at you real fast when you
compound couple Gates you have this
crazy install thing which like okay so
just think about like when you're doing
consumer anything every click you're
losing 10% of your users especially if
I'm doing this targeted to install
Netflix like I have to install Netflix
as app store get a big scary sheet and
I'm like okay I'm a normie like I don't
know what this is but it looks scary and
then you have to navigate inside their
thing and you had to click again and
it's like another big scary sheet and
Netflix has got to be like no it's okay
it's cool it's Netflix's virus like it's
fine and by the time you get to the end
of this chain it's again it's like
Netflix could do this now on Android I
don't think they have and maybe Nico's
point about it just being oneth the
revenue that's just not enough incentive
for them to do this as a developer I'm
just thinking like God I got to make
this stupid app store work I got to do
all this I got to maintain all this crap
I got to do all this billing now we got
this exposure to the CTF and all this
crap for what so we can charge $999
instead of $13 on the App Store Right
Netflix is doing fine without charging
the payments at all I guess gets into
like The Meta of like I think that was
Apple's point right I think this was the
purpose of the way theyve complied was
that to like induce maximum pain while
staying as close within the regulations
as they can because frankly they've got
a monopoly on their users time and
dollars and they don't want to let that
go and that's where I think this as a
starting point for negotiation really
interesting because maybe the most
straightforward thing for the EU to do
to make the dma more impactful is say
apple you can't charge 50 cents that's
not a fair and reasonable fee you can
only charge 10 cents and if that's the
case then the calculus of how all this
works out looks really different I'm
gonna go full Milton fredman here and
just be like that's what markets are for
basically we now have a duopoly of the
EU and apple which are probably
similarly sized in market cap right
being like being like 50 no one it's the
same thing they're both corporations of
people trying to like achieve something
what we're trending and this is where
I'm going to really put on my tin foil
hat is we have created a perfect trap
for regulatory capture because what's
gonna happen is Apple's going to like
dance to use dance they're gonna make it
work they're going to do all this work
they're going to build this super
complex thing that they alone can comply
with that's built for them to be alive
while yes we've now like created space
for new entrance at the low end anybody
who gets anywhere close to this
gatekeeper thing is going to have this
ceiling that they can't penetrate
because now they have to be a gatekeeper
as well like meta is already considered
a gatekeeper is this gatekeeper law
Inception where like if meta has an App
Store now their app store also has to
allow extra app stores or something like
this the things that we don't know yet
which makes it a bit harder to really
understand the opportunity or the
possibility of new marketplaces is like
what is that burden actually I know we
know high level what new Marketplace
have to do that to have the mill in this
like specific checks that they have to
do before they distribute software we
have to understand how costly that is
for them to understand if it could make
sense and then there's also some
questions around these scare sheets how
aggressively are actually being pushed
in user's face is there some ability to
adjust it somehow at your own language
so I think there's like some things that
are not 100% defined so it's hard to
understand I spent time with man talking
about this yesterday the founder of
backbone the mobile Marketplace a
controller and the software piece of it
and I think there's a specific examples
again where this makes a lot of sense
right like there's full price games that
are now being released on the iPhone
that's string now for example example is
coming to iPhone is $20 right it's not
like high volume yet these type of games
on the App Stores but you already have a
significant number of users that are
using the backround to play games and
that have the software layer that
already downloads a lot of apps with
that right is there a world where you
say look guys we can offer you higher
margins we make all margins on it as
long as the costs are somewhat under
control it is for us very well possible
to have a Marketplace on top of our
existing user base that actually enables
gaming distribution and I think there's
some people that are specifically
positioned already in that they can take
advantage of this potentially and then
there's some of the bigger players like
epic that just do it because it's
ideologically what they think should be
done but as soon as we have marketplaces
that do get to scale and offer a real
alternative to the app store for a
specific Niche then the calculus becomes
much more attractive then when we get
what we want which is like the appsort
to actually concede some things right
then I'll be happy then I will you know
what I'll move to Brussels I'll wear my
little blue shirt withar ring I will go
full EU congratulations it worked I'm
just like how long are these Cycles
going to take it's been years for us to
get anything and so now we're going back
to the an moot again and like we have to
like do another cycle and then literally
I think what's gonna happen is Sam mman
or somebody's gonna build an AI phone
that's gonna obsolete the iPhone and
then this is going to be like the
biggest waste of energy of all time you
know obviously I wake up in cold sweats
at night thinking our apps going away is
the iPhone going away and I don't think
I see an immediate path to that but it
would be naive to think that this model
exists forever and I think stuff like
the dma what's happening now called it
in shid ification like to use that term
it's like we're seeing the inchi
ification of the App Store the
unintentional positive here is that this
will create I think hopefully
opportunity maybe a company with an
already present base like backbone then
can then lever that into a store which
then can maybe lever that into a device
because it could be the same case for
epic and that's what actually breaks
Apple's Monopoly but that's a lot of
Bank shots I want to pull on two threads
that na brought up one earlier and one
just now is that these thirdparty
marketplaces probably make the most
sense in two specific cases out of the
gate right like evolving over time maybe
things change whatever but like out of
the gate so far I'm seeing two things
based on Nico's comments is one is that
if you're a AAA game and you charge up
front so like I can Envision under these
rules a AAA game store launching as a
third- party Marketplace you pay $50 up
front for your AAA game Nintendo could
launch the switch store with backbone as
a controller and you pay $30 up front
for the game now that gives you I mean a
decade of your 50 cents a year is five
bucks that's still lower than the market
places be paid up front and that's a
like a weird C no it's totally free it's
like the market I know but how do you
enfor how do you enforce the download on
that I guess this is the only reason to
download it is because you've paid $30
or something like this right yeah like
you can only download the app if you've
paid the $30 in this because the
marketplace I mean from my understanding
again maybe there's other details but my
understanding is like the marketplace
has like full control over the business
model within the marketplace so Nintendo
could come along with a Nintendo switch
Marketplace app it could all be paid up
front their premium games $60 for tear
of the kingdom and with a $60 upfront
payment that 50 Cent platform core
technology fee even if you have to pay
it recurring is a tiny little fee you
also to
lose though you have to pay for
everybody's CTF for the market download
but for the marketplace downlo yeah the
marketplace has to be the free download
but then subsequent downloads can be
limited so that's I think a really
interesting opportunity created by the
dma that could be done immediately under
the current rules with the current fee
structure the second one that I think
Nico kind of alluded to is a more B2B
marketplace where when you know you're
going to have a much higher LTV
and you can design the store around
those kind of limits maybe you have to
sign in with your corporate account
before you can download an app maybe
there's some other hurdle to enforce the
not downloading unless you already have
an account with that provider whatever
there could potentially be this
opportunity for high LTV especially B2B
but maybe even high LTV consumer
marketplace where there's some other
kind of gate to protect against that
core technology fee and again with some
limit on the licky lose downloading it
and starting a free trial and never
paying you a penny there's potential for
these high LTV apps to join a
marketplace where there are some
limitations in place and that could
happen today even with all of the fees
and hurdles you have to jump through
we'll see no comments from the gallery I
am so confused I Miguel and I were
talking about yesterday is like they
made it just too confusing for anyone
human brain to really like wrap their
head around and I think that was the
point 153% I can get that that I
understand this there's one too many
variables there's too many nonlinear
relationships between things I think
that's made it very difficult I will
stand up and say that everybody on this
call do not switch to the new business
model like do not like it is at best a
bad idea at worst like a huge
distraction at least wait let somebody
else do it because like Nico's talking
about a lot of companies that are sort
of these very specific cases they tend
to be bigger they know who they are and
they're going to be able to test this in
appropriate way if you're like our
Legion of Indie apppp developers and
Apple's right 99% of developers don't
get like allured by the 2% because I
don't know if you'll be able to switch
back I don't think it's a worthwhile
trade if you are in this face when n was
talking about where like certain
companies are kind of screwed by the
current terms it prints them from doing
certain things then it might be worth
doing the math on but again I think it's
a pretty risky bet I wouldn't be the
first company to stick my neck out on it
let's put it that way I'd want to like
figure out how it plays out a yeah in
The Meta we haven't discussed yet is
that we're also just talking about the
EU so like we pulled Revenue cat numbers
and from all of our customers App Store
specific EU specific revenue is 12% so
even Nintendo coming out with like a
switch store that's a lot of work to
build the marketplace to do all that
kind of stuff to maybe move the needle
on 12% of your revenue and of course
with switch they're selling hardware and
probably making some profits on that at
this point in the console Evolution and
all that so there's like a million
different caveats but yeah I think it's
interesting that you also have to filter
to the views of like this is not a
global thing we're only talking about
five to 15% of the total revenue and
then you're talking about all these
hurdles to jump through all the new code
and other things you have to do to be
able to do these things Yen you were
gonna say something yeah I mean I was
just gonna comment both Jacob's and your
comment so I think on Jacob's comment I
would completely agree with what Jacob
said I think the big wild card there is
the the third party app stores third
party app marketplaces or whatever I
think that's the only thing that could
really change the game but I also think
the likelihood of that happening and
happening quickly are relatively low
maybe epic is going to launch the
fortnite store so like we'll see what
happens with that I mean I rant some
numbers and it doesn't seem like a very
attractive proposition hey they already
spent a hundred billion dollars find the
Apple yeah exactly another 100 million
just to ideological more than anything
so that's gonna happen that's one as
I also think some of this will be
litigated in some way or another right I
mean you know of course Tim Sweeney is
already cursing over on Twitter about
this and might take apple to cord over
this I'm sure Spotify is going to do the
same so I think that's the second aspect
I think there David you said I mean yes
it's EU only but I bet that a bunch of
regulators across the world are also
basically watching this space and kind
of seeing what happens right and seeing
like is this experiment successful or
not and I learned from that because
maybe not so much in the US because
obviously I mean for one thing apple is
a US company but the world is Big
outside of the us as well so we'll see
what happens I think that that's really
met yeah you have to presume this is the
response model they'll use you know
there was an open markets act in the US
that was kind of very similar they
didn't get a lot of traction but if it
ever did yeah they would be no and I
mean I think apple is going to keep
behaving this way and like doing the
minimum that they can I think that
that's become very very evident over the
last two or so years it's a little bit
of a shame because in the end probably
the worst thing is that we end up with
app business models that are completely
fixed and fixated by regulatory bodies
with no ability to have any flexibility
but we'll see what happens again I think
there's probably a few more moves to
watch here before I mean there doesn't
seem to be a first mover Advantage here
to try and take advantage of this yeah
this is probably a good place to wrap up
all the whole conversation and tight in
a nice little bow I think a good point
Yan is that this is again just one more
step in like a multi-year multi
Battlefield War that's going on between
Apple and developers and consumers and
Regulators what's the end game for apple
and this is what's so frustrating to me
is just that Gruber had a good line in
one of his posts recently said the last
thing you want to do if you're a sports
team in a high stakes sporting event is
piss off the refs and like that's what
Apple's doing it's like they're just
inviting more regulation
South Korea has already responded to
app's quote compliance in South Korea
saying that they don't think app's
actually complying and are threatening
to find them like Apple's pissing off a
lot of people like they're squandering
developer Goodwill they're pissing off
Regulators consumers are starting to
hear seem super table did you see the
screenshot I show yesterday 14-year-old
son is like apple sucks because he just
sees all the YouTubers complaining about
like he want an Android phone Tim
Sweeney responded on my tweet today well
why not build a new phone phone he says
it cost $300 billion I'm like Apple's
worth 3 trillion that's a 10x return
build a new phone for $300 billion I
think that is the natural cycle of it
right platform takes over earns Monopoly
becomes shitty and unresponsive between
other things somebody goes like okay
there has to be a better way and then
somebody invents the better way and then
we continue on into the future and it's
great can I add two last things um that
I think maybe interesting to hear the
one is like another opportunity that we
haven't touched upon and this is just I
guess my mind but I'm thinking okay
since we have the status quo and we know
apple is cheeky like it's really
interesting because I had a lot of
developers be like really upset with
apple about this and I understand it but
like it's clear what Apple's incentives
are right and of course they're trying
to as much as possible avoid to lose
revenue and this is a way that they can
comply but also like make it very
difficult and so we have to find a way
to take opportunities out of it other
than the ones that we discussed I think
there's one here which is the 600 new
apis that are being released which I
think is like something not to be
dismissed right and I don't know exactly
what the Innovation from that will be
but I'm sure there's going to be
entrepreneurs out there that will figure
that out and I think that's going to be
quite interesting it also will be good
for your businesses and I think on the
marketpl aspect is something I think
because yes it will be hard and we will
have to Kickstart it from some position
of power and it could either be existing
players big players that just do it
ideologically but also this is where
Venture can be very helpful right these
are the types of things that you can
actually fund with Venture Capital where
it's may be very hard economically for
the first four five 10 years to actually
get to a place where you can have the
scale but that is something that Venture
could enable and I would love to talk to
people that are building in trillion
dollar swings right there aren many
trilon dollar swings right yes the API
call out is a good one it's sort of an
area we didn't get to touch on too much
for my closing take it was cool to see
apple announce so many new API sort of
under the hood here that kind of bodess
well for us and what we're building
collectively us not just Runway but then
zooming out to the meta I think this
Singularity event the iPhone coming into
existence that Jacob talked about before
like a lot of this does feel like just
shuffling things around some different
numbers to distract everyone and figure
out where to move but it's little steps
and I think that's one of the take-homes
for us so far it's not a big shift yet
it's a move in a Direction but for the
really big stuff I think there might be
a bigger Singularity event that's on the
horizon so getting my AI brain chip I'm
already pre-ordered doesn't even have um
Yen for the benefit of the listeners on
the subclub podcast and people who are
watching this on YouTube after the fact
you've been answering a lot of great
questions in the Q&A are there any that
you feel like are particularly Salient
that we kind of didn't hit or maybe
questions folks who aren't live and
don't have access to the chat that would
be especially interesting to kind of
answer live or maybe even kick around as
we wrap up there's a bunch of questions
around what we will do so I'll get to
those later there's a bunch of people
asking whether this business model is
per app or per developer account my
understanding from reading this is that
because it's an amendment to the
developer agreement that is probably per
developer so you can't like opt in some
of your apps opt out some of the other
apps there were more questions around is
this reversible or not so here we said
earlier maybe it might be eventually
reversible but right now the documents
that Apple released say it's a oneway
decision so I think they can't make it
reversible right it's like Insurance
like you can't buy insurance after the
fact you know what I mean like I heard
rumors that it will be reversible but
then thinking through even if Apple did
by like the letter of the law to comply
to the EU or whatever make it reversible
the business implications of making it
reversible are pretty daunting again one
of the fine print I haven't found it in
the fine print but somebody told me that
if you're installed from a Marketplace
the App Store can't overwrite that app
and if you're installed from the App
Store The Marketplace app can't
overwrite that app so you're trying to
move somebody from Marketplace to the
app store or from the App Store to the
marketplace you have to specifically say
please go delete the app store version
and then you have to have some like data
loss prevention mechanism in place there
and then say go to the marketplace and
download it so like even if it were
reversible like the business
implications of trying to reverse this
decision are pretty daunting here's a
question that I think might be easy to
hit but do we think Google Play will
change this rules in a similar manner
they fall under the gatekeeper
restrictions right do they need to do
anything in addition to what they
already do to come into compliance Eric
sufer had a really good post on this was
talking about how because they already
do allow side loing and actually are way
less restrictive about how they do the
side loading there are things that apply
but a lot of what we talked about today
don't apply because they're already open
in those ways I know you read that post
is there something specific you want to
call out yeah I'm not 100% sure but my
guess is that they will probably have to
allow alternative inab payments as well
but already doing that with billing
Choice yeah exactly exactly so that's
basically that so that's how does how
does Google look like the ones who
didn't make a big mess of this right
like usually their stuff's like
complicated I actually I think Google's
actually doing some really smart stuff
like they're I'm going trade in my
iPhone y'all time to get on
Android this is what I was kind of
hoping Apple would do to comply with the
dma was actually following Google's
footsteps because with billing Choice
Google is saying and maybe I'm G to get
the details wrong yens you may have dug
a little deeper into this but they're
saying okay you can have alternate inapp
purchases you can use thirdparty credit
cards you can do whatever payments you
want all we're going to say is that on
the pay wall you have to have both
Google Play billing and your third party
billing and let users pick and then they
do also still charge I think a
commission on the third party billing
but that is complying even more so with
the letter of the law and also does
create user choice but is also still
kind of good for Google because a lot of
users are just going to pick Google
billing anything else to add on Google
bilding Choice Y no I think that's it
and what's been established there and I
think that's just not going to change
unless a regulator steps in is that both
Apple and Google basically say well if
you're using our app store for
everything except payments will
basically take over a very small
percentage of our commission right so
for Apple here it's 3% for Google it's
been 4% I think which just means like
economically speaking for the most part
it doesn't make a lot of sense for
developers unless they have specific
reasons let's say for example you use a
third party payment provider that
provides alternative payment methods
that are very important for your user
base or whatever right then that is
something to consider but in most cases
like Apple and Google actually have a
pretty wide range of different payment
methods in different countries now right
so that it's unclear but I mean there's
certainly Choice there I would agree
with that I'm just gonna tag on to the
wrap-up here and just say I posted
yesterday a poll as to what people would
choose old model or new model I think it
was like 8020 people old model new model
I just ran a new poll and I posted it in
the chat so everybody that attended the
webinar here after hearing my official
recommendation I just want to know how
much weight that carries and I'm curious
what people think after learning a bit
more about the rules they're excited
about the new model the old model so
links on my Twitter for the poll nice y
any other pressing question so just from
the questions panel that because there a
bunch of questions around like what will
Revenue cat do will Revenue cat launch
an alternative app store will Revenue
CAD support alternative app stores will
Revenue CAD support alternative payments
in app so I think certainly we're
discussing all of those I think us
launching an alternative app store is
probably the one that is the least
likely supporting alternative app stores
to the extent that is possible and to
the extent that they become relevant I
think that's all absolutely going to be
on the agenda right so like maybe not
the Epic store because we're focusing
more on subscription apps than games per
se but if there's any feasible
alternative app stores then we will
definitely do our best to support those
alternative inapp payment ments I think
right now they don't look super
attractive but we are working on some
things that you know just for more
flexible billing across platforms so
that's something that's very much top of
mind and where we should be able to move
quickly as well to the extent it becomes
relevant yeah those were kind of I guess
the three very very big questions about
like what will Revenue cat do so I have
a I have a more straightforward answer
gonna help developers make more money
yes whatever it takes whatever it takes
prevent them from making less money yeah
that's the whole
yeah that's a good way to frame it like
if we think it's going to make
developers make less money we probably
won't go through all the effort to
support a random store that we don't
think is actually going to benefit
developers but if we see opportunities
that really will help developers make
more money we're going to be working on
my greatest failure in life will be if I
cling on to an existing business model
to the point that I'm regulated by the
EU so make sure that we adapt to the
changing market and respond to Consumers
all right well let's just go around the
horn one final time and just kind of do
a wrap up Nico what are your closing
thoughts on this
mess my brain is wired in a way that I
always try to understand like what is
the opportunity here and so I think yes
I agree with Jacob that nobody should
rush and it has to be understood well
what this means and even we don't
understand it yet right there's a lot of
new ones still to be defined there's
also still probably negotiations around
the actual final terms and so I think
let's wait but I do believe that every
time there's Chang as opportunity and
there's going to be smart entrepreneurs
or existing companies that will take
those opportunities and I'm excited
about it I think it really plays into
the thesis I think some companies will
just remain the way it is but I think
for others new marketplaces prummer High
converting apps that also want to do
team accounts and potential emergence of
new marketplaces are things that I for
me those are new themes that I will be
looking into and so I'm cautiously
optimistic that there's going to be some
benefits from this and also that the
final results will be better than what
we know today Gabe I think highest level
not as much of a massive shift as it
might seem but a move in that direction
like I said I think maybe lower level
maybe nearer term extra work and kind of
headache figuring this out for folks I
think that's an interesting challenge to
think about that from the other side and
how you can help folks with these
changes awesome yens it's interesting
never adul I think that's that that's
kind of who would have
thought who would have thought yeah no I
think that that's kind of it to me but
my advice for app developers would be I
mean definitely keep up to date but
there's probably no need to rush to make
any decisions and it's certainly not the
first move in this chain of events that
has been unfolding for like the last at
least two and a half years it is an
important step a significant step but
more steps are going to come and this
game is far from over yet so that's my
take here and we'll see what happens in
this space especially I think on the
alternative app Marketplace that's what
I think is the most interesting is there
going to be anything that really makes a
material difference there and Jacob
saved you for last so you could rant my
boy they butchered my beautiful boy they
out the store I'm all for competition I
want better deals for developers I want
Tim Sweeney to be able to do whatever he
wants and make all the money he wants
like I want everybody to be happy
obviously but I can't help but be like a
little sad that we had kind of a pretty
simple kind of a pretty decent little
deal and it helped a ton of people and
it created this whole entire appicon
and I don't see immediately that what's
happening is good for that what I see
happening is creating more complexity I
see it risking the entire space and I
don't know maybe it's the maturing of it
the inch ification whatever you want to
call it and maybe it's for the best and
this will create the next thing and all
of it's good but I can't help lament a
little bit the Simplicity we might be
losing with this model that's worked
pretty well for a decade even if you
know not everybody's happy and whatever
you can't debate that it has created
more wealth and more value value and
more software than anything we had ever
tried before and then to just like
murder it over 2% feels a little
shortsighted I don't know but maybe
that's just being sentimental onwards
into the future and we'll be here for
the next thing too I don't think any of
us want to spend our time like
prognosticating about European
regulation right like we just want to
make apps so like the sooner we can get
back to that the better all right well
I'm G to wrap up with my hot take since
I'm the host I get to close it all out
but Jacob I think your take is and I am
on the same page but with a slightly
different spin so I started my career as
an indie developer who exactly as you
said like capitalized on this incredible
business opportunity like sitting in my
little condo in San Marcos Texas in 2008
I shipped apps to the world and saw
people buy in Saudi Arabia in India and
all over the world and it was so simple
for me to build that business and to
build this career on the App Store and
so like personally as a kind of longtime
Apple Fanboy that's struggling with my
fanboyism but then also like as a
longtime developer who's made millions
of dollars and had millions of downloads
on the App Store I'm sad too but while
you spun it back around to the EU and to
the regulation I'm personally a lot more
frustrated with apple I don't think we
would have gotten to this point had
Apple made more concessions to make it a
better place more opportunity and again
Google's already kind of leading on this
front
they drop the fee for subscription apps
to 15% that's actually probably a pretty
good deal for most apps to not even
worry about billing Apple's obstinance
in sticking to this 30% is part of
what's creating that inch ification and
so as much as the EU laws are complex
and hard to parse and all that kind of
stuff and we're regulating things into
the ground like apple had a choice here
and I personally think they're making
the wrong choice they're pissing off
developers they're pissing off
regulators and it's bleeding over into
sentiment from consumers like my
14-year-old son and I think that's like
you said sad for the platform that we
all actually kind of care
about time to start a phone company it's
time it's the moment it's been fun thank
you for people who got this far on the
podcast thank you Nico for joining thank
you Gabe for joining thank you Jens and
Jacob for being here and to be
determined this will probably not be the
last webinar probably not the last
podcast where we discuss all the
implications and let's see what the EU
says let's see what Apple does let's see
what Tim Sweeny does and we'll talk to
you all again soon thank
you thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub do.com to
join our private
community